All right, welcome back everyone. It's
September 25th and we're in chapter 4.
So,
does anyone want to start with any part
of chapter 4?
any
section or quotation or question that
that they have or that was already
written down by a previous participant
or just any part of four to jump into.
I have a quick question just about
notation and conventions. Um, and this
is just to sort of orient me to
>> Wait, you you muted there for a second.
Would you just orient to me to which
domains this particular notation is most
associated with
>> statistics?
>> Okay.
>> Y being observation and X being latent
state is statistics.
And then there are some slight
differences between like the
mathematical control theory and the
engineering applied control theory for
like which variable they might use for a
transition matrix or for a control
variable.
But it's it's largely grounded in in
this relationship between observables
and unobservables.
Any
other just random interesting quote from
the chapter or a question?
Or we can look at some of the previous
questions or we can skim through the
chapter.
Okay, let's kind of just go through the
chapter, but write in the chat or raise
your hand if you if you want to um
proceed. Okay, starts with everything
should be made as simple as possible but
not simpler. But isn't that the
question? And
the good news is that's where the basian
information criterion comes into play
which is like rewarding things for
fitting but then penalizing them for
having more parameters because you
always fit better by having more
parameters in the model but then there's
some kind of bend where you're getting
diminishing returns. So that's a theme
that comes up again and again is like
how do you trade off those dual
imperatives of fitting well but not
overfitting or simplifying but not
oversimplifying.
Okay, introduction paragraph
complements the preceding chapter's
conceptual treatment with a more formal
treatment which is kind of a funny way
to begin the chapter because it's like
wait
after chapter two and three a more
formal treatment. It's like yes. Um but
now in terms of the
low road and the high road which were
covered in chapters two and three, now
we're in chapter 4. We took both of the
approaches to the place. Now this is
where the actual generative models are
going to be described.
A key focus is on different ways of
handling time. specifically time as
discrete time steps or continuous
flow which gets revisited in chapter
seven and eight.
Okay. 4.2
picks up with the notion of the basian
brain which is uh one of the sort of
family slash
predecessor
theories of just thinking about what
organisms or brains do in terms of
basian inference problems which get
broken down into these two
broad categories of cognition.
inbound
perception
doing something about inferring the
state of the world and then action
specifically
um
because exact inference even on a
computer is often infeasible. There's
all kinds of heruristics and even if the
computation were feasible on a computer,
we would it it's basically just a
foregone conclusion to say that's well
like quote that's not what the organisms
really doing. It's like right it's a
computer program. It's not what the
organism is doing. Um,
so they're going to highlight why the
use of free energy statistics are useful
in these generative models
and what those models are about.
The chapter is more technical than 1.3
and some of these topics are in the
appendices, others are just a good side
readings. But linear algebra, so systems
of equations with variables that are
fixed or or known or unknown,
differentiation,
looking at integrals and derivatives,
and the tailaylor series expansion for
the continuous time setting of moving
further and further away, estimating a
function through using derivatives.
they return to B theorem and just write
it out. X is a latent state. Y is an
observation. And there's all different
kinds of ways to kind of reconfigure B
equation depending on which parts you
know and which parts you don't know. But
that was visited in chapter 2 with the
frog and the apple.
Okay.
uh
here takes an interesting turn into some
of the fundamental properties of logs.
So I think we will have a
yeah
so it's often brought up like why do why
use a probability versus a log
probability?
So there's a few computer science
reasons and then there's quite a number
of analytical reasons.
So this is a good link but this this
kind of information can be found
anywhere which is
these these kinds of calculations
make log probabilities very amenable to
statistics.
So the log of a product is the sum of
the logs. So if we wanted to have the
probability of a coin flip and rolling a
dieice those are independent. So we want
to multiply the probabilities but then
the logs get summed. So there's
calculations that are independent can
just be summed in logs and and um
similarly for divisions and subtraction.
Um exponentiation
is well behaved in logs. And then
there's some computer science
considerations like if it's a very small
number you want it's easier to store a
large number than a tiny number on a
computer like 1 billion rather than 1
billion. And so if we're dealing with
low with given events that have low
probability it can be easier to store
that as a log probability. Um, and then
there's this Jensen's inequality
which is the log of an average is
greater or equal to the average of a
log.
And that is going to come into play
through these steps described here.
um basically as as a confirmation that
we'll be able to uh approach the log
probability which is the value we
actually care about and have that as a
bound for a free energy value.
That's an interesting section. We can
come back to it but returning
carry on. So basically there's there's a
divergence that can be calculated
um
separately from the overall level of
likelihood.
that matters because
in terms of incremental sequential opt
optimization
what's really important is that there's
a procedure to improve step by step not
necessarily that you have the best
estimate of the overall exact likelihood
of something happening.
So that's primarily looking for
attractable evidence maximization
scheme.
So that's the KL divergence and and
there's some other choices there, but
that's um just kind of revisiting that
foundational idea. Okay, this is a
really this is kind of the key section
of the key chapter and it relates to a
lot of the questions that people have
about what is free energy and a lot of
times there's there's ambiguity of like
well what what about this situation and
what is the free energy of this fly in
that situation and it's like this is an
example of a quote that makes it very
clear that free energy is a property of
models not of systems. So free energy is
a characteristic of maps not
territories. That's kind of this core um
meme that helps forestall a lot of other
nonsequators.
To calculate the free energy we need
three things data a family of
distributions and a generative model
which is the prior and likelihood.
So free energy is a calculated statistic
with those things in hand.
If those values are in hand, you can
make this calculation. If the values are
not in hand, it would be like saying,
well, what's the regression co
coefficient or what's the sum of squares
of this linear regression?
But I'm not going to tell you what the
data are. So, it's kind of like an
incomplete sentence, but it's it's it's
just interesting that this is the narrow
form of of um what free energy is, but
that that helps contextualize like how
broadly people kind of take it beyond
that. All right.
They are going to highlight a few
different generative models in this
section.
There are models with categorical
variables in their state spaces
and there are models with continuous
variables in their state spaces.
And then there's this other axis which
is whether time is handled as a discrete
sequence of events or whether time is
handled as a continuous differentiable
flow. So kind of explored that before,
but there's like 2 by two quadrants in
terms of this taxonomy of generative
models
and you can have hybrids that that
include all all four quadrants or
whatever you want. But just at the first
pass, there's discrete time and
continuous time. And then within either
of those time handlings, you can either
have a discrete categorical variable
um like hot, medium or cold. Or you
could have a continuous variable in the
state space like on a scale of 1 to 100.
Okay, figure 4.2 is a really nice
background figure that that um you know,
again, there's infinite ways to
reconfigure these textbooks. The whole
point is there there's not a linear
path, but this is a great background
concept to get a better handle on what
these graphs that we're going to see are
all about and to connect it to causal
reasoning.
So this is kind of the top left is like
there's a latent variable that gives
rise to an observable
and then you can talk about well what
what is the what is the raw py what's
just the distribution over y's like and
then there's what is the distribution
over y conditional upon x like what's
the overall temperature distribution and
then there's what's the temperature
distribution conditional upon it being
daytime or night time um And then
there's other causal settings like there
could be one latent factor that causes
two observations.
There could be two causal factors that
cause one observation.
There could be a chain of causal
consequences that lead to an
observation.
So this is just like thinking
compositionally or graphically about
causal flows in these kinds of
structural models.
Um,
in the parametric statistic setting,
this is often called a structural
equation. So they'll take a big data set
and then they'll they'll graph out like
connections just based upon kind of
correlations or like if you account for
this correlation then this correlation
becomes stren stronger or weaker. Um so
those are like kind of corrected or
calibrated correlation statistics
and then what causal logic or what
graphical modeling does.
This is the kind of pearl direction is
is just
explicitly include
causal factors and observations.
So again, that's what these graphs are
showing is you have Yeah.
Go ahead.
>> Oh. Um, what is the way to get from an
equation or a data set to drawing one of
these diagrams? like are they visual
sort of aids or are they
like actually capturing uh something
mathematical and like there's a right
and a wrong way.
So to determine
causal
diagrams for data sets is kind of like
it's sometimes called structured
learning. But that's kind of the the the
that would be like the generic
superpower would be to take data like
numerical data and then propose
causal models.
Now just like the quote at the beginning
of the chapter, there's potentially an
infinite number of causal models
depending on which variables you want to
include or not. So it isn't just that
there's one but then on the other hand
sometimes you explicitly
want to specify the causal model and
then you want to generate synthetic data
and then with that synthetic data you
want to see whether you can recover the
parameters like determine that you did
have the correct causal model underlying
it. But that is this whole area of
causal discovery and modeling
is basically how do you draw those edges
among empirical variables
and then how do you propose and connect
up other latent variables
to make the most robust performance
account.
And then it's like, well then do you
want fewer variables that explain the
data less well or do you want more
variables that explain it better? And
that's where that basian information
criterion comes into play because you're
kind of comparing a portfolio
of models
and then they can be compared in
different features like um how sensitive
are they to the amount of data or to the
variability of the data or how models
that have fewer or more parameters.
Yeah, Benjamin.
Okay, so I mentioned I'm like one or two
chapters ahead, but without context in
mind like this. I like this uh diagram.
It's showing some causality between
these variables later and this is the
question like later I think in the book
it says the generative model itself may
have priors about your beliefs of on
causal structures like this right so
uh it this is like applying it to the
baze equation which is like pretty clear
we we all believe we all we all have the
same beliefs about what the causal
structure of bay law is but is it also
true that like this concept's useful
Because when designing models later, the
model also might have in its priors
beliefs about causal structures that are
more tenuous or about less known
structures than bas law. Does that make
sense?
>> Yeah. Well, one of the great parts about
basian modeling, whether it's used as
the scientific tool to specify models or
whether you're talking about making an
agent who is a basian causal reasoner
and will be proposing its own possible
distributions is like it makes the
priors explicit.
you can see where something has just
been fixed like and the buck does have
to stop somewhere
and you can see where that is like the
prior of it being um day or night is
just 50/50
and then someone else says oh it's not
50/50 I think it's actually drawn from
this other distribution
okay well what is your distribution on
that so like a hyper hyper prior or a
hyper parameter
but eventually you're going to get to
some distribution that you're drawing
the highest hyper prior from.
Even if it's a uniform distribution or
if it's what whatever shape it is, but
it it has to be drawn from somewhere or
be a fixed number. And then that's kind
of the fun about the delta distribution.
It's it's a quirky distribution, but
it's basically just a spike on the line.
So that's like this the it's it's it's a
very unique distribution. It's basically
just a number,
but it's like a number wrapped up like a
statistical distribution which lets you
say okay um and my my prior for the
number of buses per day is eight
period.
And then that gets all the semantics of
being a full distribution even though
it's literally just the number eight.
this graph.
They keep on discussing it and then they
pivot to this kind of core Rosetta Stone
image which is also the graphical
abstract of what's to come in chapters
seven on the top and eight which is like
okay so that was the general setting of
latent variables and observations and
the ways that we can have these kind of
um operators that
can do all the stuff that we would
expect with Legos. does like do a
transformation or merge or split.
Well, now that's going to get brought
into play with these graphical models of
a simple cognitive system
and uh
yes Anna wrote circles versus square are
relevant for understand. Yeah, great
great point. So the circles are random
variables themselves
and then the
squares are distributions
that have the given um meaning. So like
one here is a probability distribution
on X giving rise to the random variable
X.
And this is going to come back again
with the message passing and the factor
graphs and and so it can be revisited at
a deeper level.
But yes,
like
on on the uh top graph here,
we have several circles and then several
squares.
The circles are the random variables
themselves
and then the squares are kind of um
distributions that get specified
when you
use the code example
you specify all of them.
So in I mean just in practice
it's not like circles and squares.
They're all variables in a statistical
model but for clarity they're they're
being drawn out this way.
Um
they talk about why they have this
different notation
between the top and the bottom even
though there's this provocative
juxiposition
to show that they have a overall
congruent shape
and the variables are placed and they're
doing the same thing roughly
um in the top and the bottom model
the the backbone of this this is the
discrete time model. The backbone of
this model with the s
is latent states changing through time.
So s of s of subtal is latent state in
the moment. Then we have the next moment
and the previous moments.
Three is a distribution
that says what is the latent state at
the next moment conditional upon the
state at this moment and the action
being selected.
So that's why three is getting inserted
there. So that's how you got from to
minus one to tow. It's how you get from
toao to to + one. So that's the kind of
back and then the initial three is your
prior over S. So that just kicks off the
chain. But you only need one kind of
initiator to the chain and then it's
just going to be this markoff transition
chain of latent states. That's the kind
of core
variable like temperature changing
through time sequence of temperature
variables. But then there's two parts.
there's like a above and a below. So at
each time point looking below
there's going to be matrix 2
leading to an observation.
So this is the two is the distribution
of observations at that time given
latent state at that time. So if it was
temperature changing through time in the
room these would be like thermometer
measurements.
So in practice, it looks like you have a
sequence of temperature observations
on your data sheet, but the way that's
being modeled is there's a latent state
that's changing through time and at each
time it's emitting an observation. So
it's not that you have a chain, a markov
chain of observations.
You have a markov chain of latent states
and each of them are going to emit an
observation. So that's the downstairs
part is the prior and then the time
dynamics of a latent state and then how
latent states emit observations at each
time point and that gets explored like
in the music example in chapter 7 and
then there's the upstairs part. So this
is the sort of sense making and
perception part which is the
relationship between observations and
latent states. And then the control
theoretic part or the action inference
part is
instead of just having a single matrix
applied again and again and again for
the transition matrix of between time
points on s pi is like the ability to
choose between different transition
matrices. So instead of just one matrix
being applied again and again which is
how a a simple markoff chain
would happen.
It's like there's multiple index cards
that can get selected
and then action selection is which
transition matrix is going to get
selected to
play the role of state transition in the
next time step.
And then how
you determine the probability of
different actions
is the whole question of action
inference.
And one way to do that which is the
reward uh learning or reinforcement
learning approach would be we're going
to associate different actions or
different action state pairs with a
value function and then we will use the
value function to either select the best
action most valued action or we'll use
the value uh value function to rewe the
distribution of action probabilities and
select from that.
So that is how most reinforcement
learning approaches work. The difference
and what is going to get explored in the
expected free energy is actually a a
more sophisticated way of directly
working with the probabilities of
different actions
which obiates the need to spec to
specify a auxilary value function or
reward function. Rather actions are just
directly evaluated in terms of their
pragmatic value which is their alignment
with preferred observations and
epistemic value which is their expected
information gain. And then how different
policies score
on expected free energy epistemic plus
pragmatic value is used to reweight the
probabilities of those actions being
taken.
And then that direct probability of
those actions is used to either select
the most likely action or draw from that
distribution to select which transition
action to take.
That's kind of at the core of the
difference in action selection between
reinforcement learning approaches and
active events.
the bottom graph,
the nodes are going to play kind of
cognitively slashfunctionally the exact
same roles, but it's important to to
note how the math and the notation are
different.
So here the backbone part instead of
being a sequence of latent variables and
their time evolution
it's actually just one variable
then its derivative and its second
derivative and etc.
So we have like
the temperature in the room through time
the rate of change of the temperature in
the room through time.
the rate of change of the rate of change
of the temperature through time.
So whereas three was playing the role of
a transition matrix
in the discrete time setting, three in
the continuous time setting is playing
the role of basically a differentiation
operator.
Two, the mapping between latent states
and observations is roughly similar, but
just noting that the observations are
not observations at t minus one, current
moment in the future. They are the
observations through time, the rate of
change of the observations and the
second rate of change.
And then this top part is uh again
playing the functional role of action
selection.
But whereas pi was playing this kind of
procedural action selection intervention
role like turn on the air conditioner or
turn off the air conditioner. Here v is
controlling the differentiation
operator.
So whereas like if we're let's say we're
in a car and we have forward or
backwards or stay the same that would be
modeled as like three different actions
you could take that would increase your
speed or decrease it or keep it the
same.
that could also be encoded, you can
imagine as three ways to in to make a
derivative from the speed to the d to
the rate of change of the speed. Like
um
if you are putting your foot on the gas,
the acceleration is plus one,
then that will propagate through the
speed increasing. Or if you're putting
on the brake, the acceleration is minus
one.
So,
they're being laid out. It's just a uh
graphful abstract for chapters seven and
eight.
And it's just highlighting that there
are these two different ways to handle
time, but that graphical models have the
flexibility to
accommodate both those settings.
I have a question.
>> Yep.
>> So I think I tracked that for the most
part except except for intuitively I
want to make sure I understand the
second graph like these line these
horizontal lines are going out further
than just three nodes right through in
this case two or three derivatives right
like that variable would be going
through like even more derivatives as
the calculation goes on. Is that is that
am I right in understanding that like
there's only these diagrams are only
three wide on the x- axis right now but
like it models an equation that would go
much w much much further and I start to
lose my intuition for what the 50th
derivative would be
here.
>> Yeah.
>> And why that's useful like why that's
useful. I get the the first one a lot
more than the second one. But I I lose
my intuition once you're doing that many
derivatives. Like what intuitively does
that correspond to for the agent?
>> Okay. So on the top um of the examples,
it corresponds to time steps. So you
could have an agent that's just
considering one time step ahead. Even if
the simulation runs for a thousand, it's
just doing two.
>> That makes sense to me.
>> Or Yeah. or the the agent's explicit
horizon could be longer and so okay then
now this question about the generalized
coordinates on on the bottom. So
ultimately you can have the model with
just
one or two or three or however many
coordinates.
Um, this was a
Let me show you what
I
>> mean. The first thing you said was kind
of helpful. Is Yeah. is the 50th
derivative. It's just the continuous
time equivalent to thinking 50 ticks
ahead in the
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
>> Yeah. That is the um Okay. So, I I was
playing with this in the um in the RX
infer toolkit
and basically Okay. I think it's in meta
analysis
and basically looked at how well does it
fit. Okay. Yeah.
So, looked at how well
Um so there's um the rows are how many
orders of generalized coordinates do you
have? One so just the just the rate of
change just you know first derivative
second derivative etc. 1 through eight,
the eighth derivative,
you know, then there's three scenarios.
There's a constant scenario that was
just like a straight line. Then there
was a peace-wise mixed scenario with
like a bunch of weird stuff happening
and then a sign. And so it's like these
are the kinds of diagnostic plots that
you can make
to empirically assess, okay, I'm getting
diminishing returns. Like for example in
the constant setting
they did no better with with more.
So in practice you are only having and
then like Kristen has been asked this
many times like how many orders and then
he'll say something like six just like
to joke but it but
it's empirical how many orders you want
to include. Yeah. Based upon how how
Yeah. So it's basically a structured
learning question. Is is it worth the
extra compute? Am I getting
interpretability?
PID control
which is the the standard engineering
you know for for heating and airplanes
and stuff like that is just three.
So
doesn't but it's cool that it exists
within this generalized setting but but
it doesn't need to go that many deep.
Okay. Le wrote um with a difference in
policy between reinforcement learning
and active inference can active
inference agent do inmodel simulations
like in planning?
Yes. Expected free energybased policy
inference is based upon explicit policy
rollouts.
I'm not sure if that addresses it but
that is how planning as inference
is done which is kind of like a chess
just in the simplest form. It just
considers all the actions at each time
step and what would be the consequences
of those actions over the time horizon
and then evaluates each of those
sequences of actions as policy sequences
and uses that to calculate expected free
energy
uses the expected observations of those
um sequences.
>> Oh, sorry. Then I I I still
don't see the difference in policy
between environmental learning and
active influence in that case because to
me it seems like they both sample policy
from the distribution
if we're in the pending case.
Is that right?
>> Yeah. So they they are going to have the
same policy space. So let's just say we
have um left or right and we have a
planning horizon of four. So both a
reinforcement learning and an active
inference approach are going to consider
the same set of policies.
But the reward learning approach is
going to associate a value with each of
those. There's going to be another value
function. Basically then there's going
to be a map between each policy and its
score
and then this policies will be selected
based upon their scoring on this other
proposed distribution which could have
been trained with data or specified ad
hoc.
Whereas in the active inference
approach, those policies are being
directly evaluated
for
their epistemic and pragmatic value
and then those direct evaluations are
used to update the likelihood of that
policy happening.
So still if you're dealing with a with a
policy planning agents it will look
ahead and it will consider the exact
same policy space.
But policies are being compared and
updated in their likelihood
based upon this measure which doesn't
invoke any other distributions like a
score or a reward.
But the score reward can be a super
useful strategy.
If you have if you have expert
trajectories and and negative examples,
you can use supervised training to say,
well, these are bad, these are good. So,
make a score function that makes more
policies that look like this and less
that look like that.
And then you don't need to explicitly
consider
the the pragmatic value or epistemic
value of policies individually.
Does that address it?
>> Yeah. I just think that the difference
is smaller than I imagined.
Like the choice of the prior here in the
pragmatic value it seems like it can be
matched one to one to the choice of the
reward model in transform learning.
>> Yes. Yeah. Exactly. Exactly.
Yes.
But
you could do that reinforce reward
learning or utility maximization is a
special case. If you don't need
epistemic value, then you don't
necessarily need to engage with any of
the epistemics of active inference.
If you're just looking for a utility
maximizer on a fixed problem,
then you're in a situation where reward
maximization is all that matters.
But if there's any epistemic
uncertainty, like even uncertainty how
to achieve that goal,
you would want to have the epistemic
value.
Yeah, thank you for the answer.
>> Yeah, and and a a great um
ran way I'll put it in the chat.
this model stream
is probably in this paper is is probably
the best
connection between reinforcement
learning
and active inference. So what's so
interesting is and also in relationship
to to this figure
it turns out that um
if you are dealing with a fully
observable situation
then you you you
can specify
yeah if there's no uncertainty with what
needs to be done or the situation there.
If you eradicate the epistemic
components of the
um problem,
you basically do reduce it down to just
a utility maximization.
But if there's uncertainty including in
parameters of the agent like what
learning rate is the best or what
forgetting rate or just other aspects of
bounded rationality within the problem
like partial observability
you do need an epistemic component.
But then if all you have is just
utility, that's where people try to make
um like a learning bonus or um
a ran way
the same author as the as is on that
stream.
So yes,
if one is certain about the reward, one
will get the reward.
Not sure how that will map to this
though. Yeah. Yeah. Like in the T-mas
later in seven.
If the mouse knows where the food is,
they don't need to do epistemic
foraging.
So if that's the situation that one is
working in where they have, you know, an
all knowing mouse,
then you get the special case. Yes. Um
and so that's why that's why we are um
fans
of the more general analytical setting
that lets us describe
the pure utility case or the pure
epistemic case with the novelty
motivation
or modulation or blends of them.
Alexandra.
>> Okay. So, related to the the perfect
mouse, um it is there a way to um
either formally instruct a an agent to
um or not. But but basically having an
agent that goes from um
taking action to increase epistemic
value at the beginning of an experiment
and then changing to
taking action to pragmatic value you
know at the end of the
experiment so that they basically get
the both best of both worlds.
Is there a way to formalize that in this
model or is that just like imply that
that is what's happening?
So
um one example of that is this epistemic
chaining which is very similar to the um
T-mas
but basically there are um there's
different cues there's different Q
locations
and then there is different locations
where there's going to be reward or not.
So it's like the only
utility function is to get the food.
So then there is the consideration,
okay, there's all these places I could
go. I could have an uncertain I could
have a a low probability of just getting
the food or there are some trajectories
of navigation which includes stopping by
locations that I expect will reduce my
uncertainty
and then how much it's going to deflect
out of its pragmatic path and how
sensitive is it that is all the work of
of the fine-tuning and the the um
developing the different diagnostics for
the model
and those are the hard like o over in
LLM world you know you'll you'll be
dealing with large training data sets
and different ways to set your learning
rates on different examples but one
piece that's easy to forget is like
nowhere in here are we talking about
using training data
This is all just based upon the
parametric
operation of these graphical models.
Those parameters could be developed from
a training data set. That's called
parametric empirical base where you
basically jumpst start your basian
inference with an empirical estimator.
But you don't need to do that at all.
But and then yeah like trying to find
models or find the right the ranges of
parameter space that would um
be exploiting when it was smart to
exploit and then exploring when it was
smart to explore.
That would be the question.
Then you'd realize well we we need some
we know that we need something that is
going to modulate between those two.
That's why we want this formalism. Okay,
Benjamin, what if you just randomize the
parameters? It works but more costly.
Yeah, which random distribution though?
That's the first question. And then the
second question is you'd want to be
visiting the space proportional to how
good those solutions were,
which is exactly
the important sampling.
So it's like that's the kind of like
oraoris moment is like we would want to
take informative actions
and useful ones and if those are one and
the same then then it doesn't matter.
Well then we could have just you know if
if we could have opened the door with
our left or right hand then it doesn't
matter but if we but it but then where
they differ we want different
sensitivities to where they differ. You
could you could say my preference for
ice cream is so high that that I don't
explore on the path. Or you could say I
have a tiny preference for this but not
that. So then what's the state space?
And then how would you explore that? And
then you'd want to sample from that
state space according to and then
according to what? And then the reward
the reward answer is according to a
value function. You want to spend time
in rewarding locations.
But that begets this whole secondary
sequence of well how did you get that?
And it's either well we trained it from
past data or we specified it ad hoc. The
active inference answer is spend time
proportional to the likelihood
which is tautological
but that's the physics grounded. It's
like the the the the molecule in the
energy well
or the ball in the well spends time
proportional to its likelihood of being
in that location based upon the energy
function.
So that's the tutology that dispenses
with the need for the reward function.
But that's definitely the trick.
But it puts it moves all the focus of
what we actually do need to do onto the
generative model which is why it's right
there between the low and the high road.
And that's why this is the crux of the
matter is what is the struct and that's
what chapter six asks about. What's the
situation? What are you really trying to
ask? What is the generative model? How
are you going to handle time? How are
you going to handle state spaces?
>> Well, that's kind of why I asked my
question is like in that because I
peaked at that chapter. It's like well
that's where the artistry comes from or
that's where like the model maker needs
to do some work. But I guess my question
is like if you just randomize all that
intuitively, it seems to me like you
would get like a useless model because
of its autology. If it's a tautological
and you don't put any work into your
like initial conditions based on like
the model designer's empirical intuition
or experience, then like I guess my
question is like it can't it can't work,
right? That's kind of my question. There
has to be some
I think uh bootstrapping based on either
like the model creators or like
empirical experience or some other
sampling of empirical data. But
>> I hear you also saying no, it could work
out if you like randomize even the value
function or something like
>> that's like the kind of AGI angle that
people go. They try to pull back to
what's the most minimal or the generic
or like what is like the generator that
will generate the like all of that. But
if you don't specify anything, there's
not going to be a generative model. If
you do specify it, it's going to be
whatever it is. Those are the two
situations.
Al um does it make sense to look at
reward in relation to precision
confidence uncertainty prediction error
decrease in the active inference
framework? Yeah, I mean there's there's
so many ways to to go with that. Like
you could say you could make a model
that prefers to reduce its error.
Another approach is people um associate
error or more error than expected with
negative veilance
and then so then then an improving model
or a model that's improving faster than
expected is is associated with a effect.
And then that
then you can like you can have a kind of
ruminating agent that looks ahead and
can and then looks at like the
variability or the overall um attainment
of different paths
and then brings that veilance or
uncertainty into the moments
and it's like that's not necessarily
computationally what you want. It
doesn't also necessarily
perfectly mapped to human experience,
but
it's like now there's something on the
table and then people can can make
variance and explore and say, well, in
this case, but um yeah, I mean there's
just so many ways to go with it. It's
just like no specific linear regression
how well it fits or doesn't will ever
kind of cast doubt on the intrinsic
coherence of the linear regression
framework.
So no specific generative model
fitting well or not
will ever make a general claim about the
intrinsic coherence of the math of the
generative models.
And then some people think that that's
like disappointed
because they want to verify the
analytical framework based upon a model
or they want to um know that a really
well-grounded mathematical basis is
going to lead to like a successful
startup or a drone algorithm that works.
But it's like all the work is on the
model creation.
Active inference by itself is is just
these formalisms that give us a kind of
controlled language to express
generative models.
But then which diagnostics and
trade-offs and the structure of those
models is is 100% on the the creator.
Okay. 441
is basically a little preview of chapter
7.
And they and then four 4.5 is a preview
of chapter 8, but it's it's intervened
upon by this important box about
blankets and message passing.
preview of chapter eight with the
generalized coordinates of motion
tailaylor series expansion.
So like if if your if the real function
were just a quadratic
then the tailaylor series expansion into
the quadratic
would explain 100% of the variance and
further derivatives would add no more
value. Whereas if it was a sinosoid
then the tailaylor series you would need
to take out infinitely far. But if it
was a sinosoid you should then pull back
to recognize that you should use a s
syosoidal generative model and then
you'd be back to having one parameter
model that would fit all the data.
So that's four
It
rehearses some fundamentals. B equation,
Jensen's inequality, the properties of
logs,
causal modeling on a graphical setting.
Then we get introduced to the Rosetta
Stone 4.3 preview of chapter 7 and 8.
Section 4.4 is a preview of chapter 7.
Section 4.5 is a preview of chapter 8.
There are some boxes with some technical
topics. Markoff blankets, message
passing, belief propagation,
generalized coordinates, lelass
approximation.
So it's quite a firecracker of a
chapter.
as as they see it. You know, again,
there's there's so many papers before
and after and other documents and you
can ask an LLM, etc. But
they felt that this chapter outlines the
basic formal ideas. You know, if we have
a better or different way, we can
publish it. We can write our own blogs
and textbooks and everything like that.
But this is really the core of
how the authors see active inference
and it sets up it's kind of the the
center of the book.
Chapter five is going to go into the
neurohysiology.
Chapter six kicks off the second half of
the book with more of the applications.
How do you make the recipe? Seven and
eight discrete and continuous time.
Chapter nine, integration of data.
Chapter 10, closing.
So this is kind of this is the um
central passages of the book
and that's thank you Ahmed.
Any last uh thought or question?
Okay,
thank you all. See you. See you next
time.
Bye.